Guide to the William F. Durand Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
William F. Durand papers
1893-1979
SC0381
Durand, William Frederick, 1859-1958
1.25 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
None.
Biography
William F. Durand, known as the Dean of American engineering, joined the Stanford University faculty in 1904, serving as professor and head of the Mechanical Engineering Department until his retirement at age 65 in 1924; he held the position of Professor Emeritus until 1958.
Durand, a 1880 graduate of the United States Naval Academy, began his teaching career at Michigan State College in 1887; in 1891 he joined the Cornell University faculty, teaching in the School of Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering.
Although his early research was in marine engineering, Durand was best known for his contributions to the science of aeronautics, specifically the development of the first variable pitch propeller. He was an original member of the National Advisory Committee on Aeronautics, serving from 1915 to 1933, and again during World War II, when he helped organize the work being done on jet propulsion.
Durand was professionally active well into his 80s. After his retirement from Stanford, he continued his research on airplane propellers, making use of Stanford's wind tunnel. He served several terms as president of the American Society of Mechanical Engineers and Sigma Xi. He was a member of a federal advisory board concerned with the Colorado River and Hoover Dam; and he worked with the Daniel Guggenheim Fund for the Promotion of Aeronautics
Scope and Content
The papers of William F. Durand date from 1893 to 1958; included with them are some biographical and scientific writings by others that relate to Durand dating to 1979. the papers primarily concern his research in engineering and aeronautics. They include correspondence, manuscripts, typescripts, research notes, reports, reprints, clippings, photographs (including some of damage to Stanford buildings from the 1906 earthquake), memorabilia, and a copy of his published autobiography. The correspondence consists mostly of carbon copies of outgoing letters from 1943 1to 1945 concerning publications, aeronautical research, recommendations, professional affiliations, Stanford University affairs, and some personal news.
Durand is also represented in three other collections within the Department of Special collections. Papers concerning design and construction of dams, M0144, contains one folder of Durand's papers concerning Boulder Dam, 1935. Science and scientists, M0133, contains several letters between Durand and R. Giacomelli, 1930. University records relating to Durand can be found in SC 064a, the presidential papers of Ray Lyman Wilbur.
Access Terms
Stanford University. Department of Mechanical Engineering. -- General subdivision--Faculty.;; Aeronautics--Research.; Hydraulics.; Marine engineering.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence, Series 1
  - Correspondence, 1917-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, January - June, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, July - December, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, and fragment, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Research and Writings, Series 2
  - ADVENTURES IN THE NAVY; IN EDUCATION, SCIENCE, ENGINEERING; AND IN WAR; The ASME and McGraw Hill Book Company, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "An Average Instrument for Polar Diagrams," JOURNAL OF THE ASME, reprint, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Biographical Memoir of Harris Joseph Ryan, 1866-1934," NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chimney formula; typescript paper, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dynamics of the Flow of Gases and Vapors; typescript paper, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dynamics of the Flow of Gases and Vapors; mimeographed paper, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - EXPERIMENTAL RESEARCH ON AIR PROPELLERS; National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics, Report No. 14; prepreint issued November, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Experimental Researches on the Performance of Screw Propellers," paper read before the society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Flow Data for Fluids in Pipe Lines," Stanford Oil Company, typescript report [possibly not by Durand], 1922 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Flow of Steam in a Long Pipe," report prepared under supervision of Dr. Durand; typescript (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "The Flow of Wate in Channels Under Steep Gradients," TRANSACTIONS OF THE ASME, Vol. 62, no. 1 (January, 1940) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Historical Sketch of the Development of Aerodynamci Theory, typescript paper, circa 1929 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "The Hydraulics of Oil Pipe Lines," JOURNAL OF ELECTRICITY, May 1, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Improved Transmission Dynamometer," TRANSACTIONS OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY OF MECHANICAL ENGINEERS, Vol. 28; reprint (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "The Interpretation of Electric Current Flow in Terms of the Electron Theory," THE JOURNAL OF ELECTRICTY, POWER AND GAS, reprint, Feb 28, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Investigation of Surge Phenomena by Means of Model Experiments," WESTERN ENGINEERING, reprint, December, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Long pipes, research notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Marine Engineering," TRANSACTIONS OF THE AMERICAN SOCIETY OF CIVIL ENGINEERS, Vol. 54, Part C, reprint, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Note on a Theorem in Mechanics," SIBLEY JOURNAL, reprint, Jan 1918 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "The Number of Longitudinal Intervals in Ship computation, as Affecting the Accuracy of Integration for Displacement," paper read before the Society of Nal Architects and marine Engineers, preprint, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "On the Control of Surges in Water Conduits," JOURNAL OF THE ASME, reprint, circa 1912 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Proposed Form of Seismograph Intended to Give a Direct Indication of the Forces in Play," [abstract], BULLETIN OF THE GEOLOGOICAL SOCIETY OF AMERCA, Vol. 20, reprint, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Science and Civilization," SCIENCE, August 20, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "The Screw Propeller: With Special Reference to Aeroplane Propulsion," JOURNAL OF THE FRANKLIN INSTITUTE, reprint, September 1914 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Some Outstanding Problems in Aeronautics, typescript paper, circa 1918 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Steam jets; manuscript draft and notes (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "The uses of Logarithmic Cross-Section Paper," ENGINEERING NEWS, reprint, Sep 28, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Biographical and Professional Papers, Series 3
  - Clippings, 1937-1958 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Conferences, 1936, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - John Fritz Medal, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Paths into the Blue, honorary dinner, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Professional associations, 1917-1956 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Quote, photocopy of typescript, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Sigmi Xi, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Student lab reports: report on flow of steam-sharp edge orifice by Lynn Reynolds,, LSJU Laboratory of Mechanical Engineering, M. E. 30, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Student lab reports: report on man power experiments by Lynn Reynolds, LSJU Laboratory of Mechanical Engineering, M. E. 37, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Writings about Durand, Series 4
  - Correspondence of Muriel T. McKinney and Dr. J. E. Wallace Sterling regarding Dr. Durand, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Munk, Max W., "Analysis of Dr. W. F. Durand's and E. P. Lesley's Propeller Tests," National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics, typescript paper, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Terman, F. E., "William Frederick Durand," YEARBOOK OF THE AMERICAN PHILOSOPHICAL SOCIETY, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Terman, F. E., "William Frederick Durand," typescript biography, circa 1958 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Vincenti, Walter G., "The Air-Propeller Tests fo W. F. Durand and E. P. Lesley: A Case Study in Technological Methodology," TECHNOLOGY AND CULTURE, photocopy, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "William F. Durand: Tributes on His 85th Birthday," AMERICAN SCIENTIST, Vol. 32, No. 2, (April, 1944) (Box 2, Folder 26)
- 1906 Earthquake, Series 5
  - Photocopy of relevant pages from Durand's autobiography (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of earthquake damage at Stanford: statue of Agassiz in the concrete, collapsed entrance gates (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of earthquake damage at Stanford: fraternity house, Quad corner, new library and gymnasium, Memorial Church, museum (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of earthquake damage at Stanford: power house and chimney, chemistry building, Memorial Church, Memorial Arch (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of earthquake damage at Stanford: back of Quad, Memorial Church, Encina; and one photograph of fire in San Francisco (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Additional Papers, 1876-1939; Series 6
  - Note Book No. 1 Cadet Engr. W. F. Durand: mimeographed sheets of algebra problems and Durand’s work solving them, 1876-77; also includes a geometry exam, 1877 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Note Book No. 2 Cadet Engr. W. F. Durand: continuation of geometry problems and exams, 1877-78 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Reprints: America's Air Service; Application of the Law of Kinematic Similitude to the Surge-Chamber Problem; Applications of Science; and Approximate Methods for the Treatment of Differential Equations, 1917-1921 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Reprints: Determination of the Current Curve Corresponding to Any Form of Alternating Electro-Motive-Force in a Circuit without Iron; Electrical Propulsion for Torpedo Boats; The Engineer and Civilization; and Entropy and Temperture-Entropy Diagrams, 1898-1925 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Reprints: The Graduate School: its New Duties; Graphical Chart for the Solution of Valve-Gear Problems; Historical Sketch of the Development of Aerodynamic Theory; and Mechanical Aspects of Aeronautics, 1917-1928 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Reprints: Note on Different Forms of the Entropy Function; On the Action of the Rudder; On the Influence of Surface on the Performance of Screw Propellers; and The Pelton Water Wheel, 1897-1939 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Reprints: A Planimeter for Averaging Radial Ordinates; A Problem Connected with the Screw Propeller; The Problem of the Colorado River; and The Problem of the Connecting Rod, 1901-1925 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Reprints: Special Methods of Determining Groups of Curves Representing Engineering Formulae; Sur un Type Special de Navires Destine au Transport des Grains ou du Minerai de Fer; Treatment of Non-Algebraic Curves for Maxima and Minima by the Use of Ordinates; and Water Hammer in Pipe Lines, 1903-1920 (Box 5, Folder 6)